(
"ai_sub_version": "3.5.1",
"generated_at": "2026-07-30T08:26:20.829158",
"lyrics_prompt_version": 9,
"subtitles_prompt_version": 18,
"complete": true,
"max_retries_exceeded": false,
"any_pending": false,
"settings": (
"ai": (
"model": null,
"model_subtitles": "google-gla:gemini-3.5-flash-lite",
"model_lyrics": "google-gla:gemini-3.1-flash-lite",
"rpm": 4,
"tpm": 250000,
"google": (
"file_cache_ttl": 10,
"use_files_api": true,
"max_storage_gb": 18.0
),
"search": (
"qps": 0.3,
"max_length": 4096,
"web_search_tool": "langsearch",
"timeout": 60.0,
"retries": 3,
"min_wait_seconds": 1.0,
"max_wait_seconds": 10.0,
"multiplier": 2.0
),
"validation_buffer_ms": 2000,
"verification_gap_seconds": 60,
"gap_verification_retries": 1,
"gap_verification_ignore_start": true,
"gap_verification_ignore_end": true
),
"split": (
"max_seconds": 300,
"re_encode": (
"enabled": false,
"fps": 1.0,
"height": 360,
"bitrate_kb": 35,
"threshold_mb": 20,
"duration_tolerance_ms": 100,
"encoder": null
),
"start_offset_min": 0
"thread": (
"uploads": 4,
"re_encode": 2,
"lyrics": 4,
"subtitles": 4
),
"retry": (
"per_run": 5,
"max_runs": 3,
"multiplier": 2.0,
"min_wait_seconds": 30.0,
"max_wait_seconds": 300
),
"log": (
"level": "info",
"timestamps": true,
"scrub": false,
"progress_bars": true,
"progress_bar_width": 80,
"progress_bar_refresh_seconds": 1.0
)
ダーダラダラダダ…
Da-dara-dara-da-da...
誰が袖に咲く幻花
Who is the phantom flower blooming on someone's sleeves?
ただそこに藍を落とした
Dropping indigo right there.
派手に色を溶かす夜に 銀朱の月を添えて
Adding a vermilion moon to the night where vivid colors dissolve.
転がるように風を切って
Cutting through the wind as if tumbling,
躓くごとに強くなった
Growing stronger with every stumble.
光も痛みも怒りも全部抱きしめて
Embracing all the light, pain, and anger.
選ばれなければ 選べばいい
If you aren't chosen, just choose.
声よ響け 夜のその向こうへ
Let your voice echo beyond the night.
涙で滲んでた あんなに遠くの景色まで響き渡れ
Echoing all the way to that distant scenery blurred by tears.
何を奏でて？ 誰に届けたくて？ 不確かままでいい
What are you playing? Who do you want to reach? Uncertainty is fine.
どんなに暗い感情も どんなに長い葛藤も 歌と散れ 残響
No matter how dark the emotions, no matter how long the struggles, scatter into song, reverberation.
ダーダラダラダダ…
Da-dara-dara-da-da...
ただ一人舞う千夜
Dancing alone through a thousand nights,
違えない帯を結べば
Tying an unwavering sash,
派手な色も負かす様に 真紅の香こそあわれ
Outshining even the gaudiest colors, the crimson scent is truly exquisite.
この先どんなつらい時も 口先よりも胸を張って
In any painful time ahead, hold your chest out rather than just your words.
描いた夢の灯りを全部辿るだけ
Just following all the lights of the dreams we sketched.
逃げ出すため ここまで来たんじゃないだろ?
You didn't come all this way just to run away, did you?
誰が袖に咲く幻花
Who is the phantom flower that blooms on the sleeve?
ただそこに藍を落とした
I just dropped my indigo over there.
派手に色を溶かす夜に 銀朱の月を添えて
On a night when colors melt gaudily with the moon,
転がるように風を切って 躙るごとに強くなった
Rolling through the wind, growing stronger with every step.
光も痛みも怒りも全部抱きしめて
Embracing all the light, pain, and anger.
選ばれなければ選べばいい
If not chosen, choose.
どんなに深い後悔も どんなに高い限界も
No matter how deep the regret, or how high the limit,
掻き消して残響
Scratch it out, reverberation.
はーい、ということで、ホロアコースティックライブ in SUMMER始まらましたー！
Hi there! So, Hololive Acoustic Live in Summer has begun!
やー！イェーイ！イェーイ！
Yay! Yeah! Yeah!
始まった！始まった！
It's started! It's started!
レッツゴー！
Let's go!
はーい、ということで、お越しくださってる皆様、ありがとうございます！
Yes, thank you so much to everyone who came today!
それでは最初に、今日はね、色んな一緒に歌っていただくメンバーがいっぱいいるんですけれども、自己紹介をそれぞれさせていただきたいと思います！
First of all, we have various members joining us to sing today, so we'd like each of us to introduce ourselves!
お願いしまーす！
Please go ahead!
まずは、ホロライブ6期生、ホロックスの博衣こよりです！白衣こよりだよ、よろしくお願いします！
First up, I'm Hakui Koyori from Hololive 6th Gen holoX! Nice to meet you!
イェーイ！
Yay!
はい、そして1曲目から来ていただいたの、まず澪しゃん先輩！
And next, joining us from the very first song is Mio-shyan!
うっちうっち、うっちだよー！大神澪だよー！ホロライブゲーマーズの大神澪でーす！
Uchi uchi, it's Uchi! Ookami Mio from Hololive Gamers!
よろしくおねがいしまーす！大神澪だよー！そして、はーい！
Nice to meet you! It's Ookami Mio! And, yep!
そして？あっ、私、あっ、私、ちゃんと自己紹介しないと！
And? Oh, me? Oh, I need to introduce myself properly!
皆さん、森カリオペです！ソロライブEnglishの死神でーす！よろしくお願いしましゅ！楽しもう、Let's have fun, everyone!
Everyone, it's Mori Calliope! The Reaper from Solo Live English! Let's have fun, everyone!
はい、こうね、お忙しい中アコースティックライブに出演していただきありがとうございます！
Yes, thank you so much for taking time out of your busy schedules to perform!
いや、こちらこそ、出演させていただきありがとうございます！ありがとうございます！ありがとうございます！
No, thank you so much for having us! Thank you! Thank you!
はい、そしてですね、今回はなんとピアノも生演奏でお届けさせていただきます！
Yes, and this time, the piano will also be played live for you all!
はい、小鳥の生誕ライブでも演奏していただきました、うぃんぐさんです！
Yes, Wing-san, who also performed at Koyori's birthday live, is here!
うわ、素敵です！美しい～！ファンサも素敵！
Wow, how wonderful! So beautiful! Great fan service!
はい、このライブはですね、最初から最後まで完全生放送！そして、生演奏でお届けさせていただきますので、吉野、吉野に…
Yes, this live broadcast is 100% live from start to finish! And with live music, Yoshino...
吉野、よろしくお願いします！吉野、よろしくお願いします！
Yoshino, please take care of us! Yoshino, please!
ま、なんでこのライブをやることになったかと言いますとですね、ま、普通の、ライブ、生誕ライブとか周年ライブって、このダンスレッスン頑張ったりとか、
Well, if you're wondering why we decided to do this live, for regular live shows like birthday or anniversary lives, we work hard on dance lessons,
ゲストパートはね、収録でやったりとか、あの後ろのねモニター作ったりとか、
record guest parts, create background monitors,
ま、とにかく準備が大変なんですよね。大変だよね。
and well, preparation is just so tough. It really is.
そうあって、ま、1つ作るのにね、すごく時間がかかるんですけど、
Exactly, making just one takes so much time,
アコースティック、アコースティックライブだったら、集まって演奏していただいて歌ったら、当日でいけるんじゃね？というのを、ちょっとチャレンジしてみたという形になっております！
but for an acoustic live, we thought, "What if we all gather, perform, and pull it off on the actual day?" So we decided to take on that challenge!
素敵じゃん！
That's wonderful!
はい、ま、でもね、歌、歌っていただくので皆さんには大変なんですけれども、今日は楽しかったよね！本当楽しかった！嬉しい！ありがとうございます！
Yeah, but since you had to sing, it was hard work, but it was so much fun today! Really fun! I'm so happy! Thank you!
何か同期を揃いみたいな感じだね。そうそうそう！でもなんか真ん中に声が入ることで、綺麗にまとまっているね！そう、このカラーリング的にね、この並びになりました。素敵すてき！
It's kind of like matching outfits. Yeah, exactly! But having the voice right in the middle ties it together nicely! Right, based on the color scheme, this is how we lined up. So lovely!
もしかしたら今ね、ちょっとあの、うん、あのコメントが止まっちゃってるかもしれないですね。コメントが壊れちゃった、壊れちゃってるかもしれないんですけど、
Also, right now, um, the comments might have frozen. The comments might have broken, we're not sure,
また動き出すと思うので、あの皆さんちょっと様子見つつ、あとトレンド今3位まで入ってるということで、ありがとうございます！
but they should start moving again soon, so please keep an eye on things, and also we're currently trending at #3, thank you so much!
すごい！早い！はい、そんな感じでね、ハッシュタグこちらホロアコースティックライブ、つけてください！はい、おねがいします！感想も全部見ますので、ぜひツイートしてください！よろしくお願いします！
Amazing! So fast! Yeah, please use the hashtag #holoAcousticLive! Yes, please! We'll read all your impressions, so please tweet them out! Thank you!
お願いしまーす！さて、1曲目は残響散歌でしたけれども、澪先輩どうでしたか？
Thank you! Now, our first song was "Zankyou Sanka", Mio-senpai, how was it?
はい、えーっと、すごい、あの、こうやって、一緒にさ歌うのめっちゃ楽しいよね！
Yes, um, it was amazing, like, singing together like this is so much fun!
楽しい！しかも歌に集中できますからね、このアコースティックだと。こう、かっこいい感じの歌をこうやって歌うのすごい楽しかったなって。
So fun! Plus, you can really focus on the singing with acoustic. Singing such a cool song like this was really fun.
もうちょっと歌も大好きだしさ
I love singing so much,
こうね最近ね歌めっちゃ頑張ってですごいうまくなったからさ
and lately I've been working super hard on singing and gotten really good, so...
レジ緊張しちゃった一曲目だからさ
I was so nervous since it was the first song!
ちょっとね、一緒に歌っててすごいテンション上がりました。ありがとうございました！
Singing along with you guys got my hype way up. Thank you so much!
ありがとうございました！
Thank you so much!
カール先輩どうですか？ おお、かっこいい曲大好きです！
Karu-senpai, how about you? Oh, I love cool songs!
いや、実はあのこの曲あんまり知らなかったから、
Well, actually, I didn't really know this song that well beforehand,
あの、なんか歌ったことなかったから、何回も練習してマジで！
and since I'd never sung it before, I practiced it so many times, seriously!
少しずつうまくなってきたかもしれないけど頑張りました！
I might have gotten a little better bit by bit, but I did my best!
わあ、素晴らしい！
Wow, that's wonderful!
でももともと知ってると勝手に思うぐらい上手だったよね。完璧にでした。ありがとう。
But you sang it so well it felt like you already knew it from the start. It was perfection. Thank you.
かっこいい曲です。
It's such a cool song.
こちらこそ。
Same here.
はい、ナイスチョイス。
Yeah, nice choice.
コメント行き返って？
Checking comments?
行き返った、よかった、よかった。よかった、よかった。見てる、見てる。
Checked them, good, good. Glad to hear it. Reading them, reading them.
はい、ということでね、小夜理的には
Anyway, for Sayori today,
今日は夏っぽい曲をそろえて、インサーバーな感じでやりたいなと思って選曲してたんですけど、
she wanted to gather some summer-like songs and do an In-Summer kind of vibe, which is what she picked, but...
結構夏の曲ってエモい曲が多くて、しっとりね。
summer songs tend to have a lot of emotional, mellow tracks.
でも1発目はやっぱかっこよくバーンって盛り上げて始めたいなと思ったので、
But since we wanted to start off with a cool, explosive hype,
これをあの、選びまして、ちょっとかっこいい2人に挟まれて、これ大丈夫かなみたいな
I chose this one, and getting sandwiched between these two cool people, I was like, "Will I be okay?"
感じだったんですけど、なんか一緒に歌えてめちゃくちゃ楽しかった！
but singing together with them was ridiculously fun!
歌えてました、かっこよく。よかった！
We sang it coolly. I'm so glad!
ありがとうございました！
Thank you very much!
はい、ということで、それではそろそろ次の曲に行くメンバーをね、お呼びしたいと思いますよ。
Right then, let's invite the members for the next song!
ビーブー！
Biboo!
イエイ！イエイ！イエイ！
Yay! Yay! Yay!
わあ、かわいいね！あーら！
Aw, how cute! Oh my!
ではイントロデュース、オッケー？ええと、ポンビージュ、ホロライブEnglishアドベントの輝く宝石、宝石ビージュだよ！
Now, introduce yourself, okay? Um, it's-a Biboo, the shining gem of Hololive English Advent, Jewel Biboo!
キラキラ！宝石！キラキラ！
Sparkly! Gem! Sparkly!
わあ、キラキラ！
Wow, sparkly!
最近ホロカミングデイズ！
Holo Coming Days recently!
小さいよ。みんな、みんな小さーい！
She's so small. Everyone is so tiny!
小さいな。みんな小さいな。
So tiny. Everyone's so tiny.
はい、ありがとう。きゅーと！
Yep, thank you. Cute!
ね、このあとビーブーシンギングはどうだ？
Say, how about Biboo's singing after this?
どうだ？緊張？ちょっと緊張？ちょっと緊張？かわいい！
How's it going? Nervous? A little nervous? A little nervous? So cute!
はい、ではこのあとはですね、2曲続けてお届けさせていただくんですけれども、次の曲は
Alright, so next up, we'll be delivering two songs back-to-back, and for the next track...
カリ先輩とビーブーの2人で！
it's Karu-senpai and Biboo as a duo!
イエーイ！レプリゼント！レプリゼント！ぺぺぺぺぺ！
Yay! Represent! Represent! Pe-pe-pe-pe-pe!
ギャグじゃない感じなのかな、どうなのかな。
Is it not a gag song? I wonder how it is.
あの、なんかちょっとヒップホップなのかな、どうなのかな、ロックなのかな。
Like, is it hip-hop? Or rock?
オーヤー！ロックンロール！
Oh yeah! Rock 'n' roll!
ロックンロール！ロックンロールかもしれない！
Rock 'n' roll! It might be rock 'n' roll!
歌えるかも？うん、かも知れない！
Can we sing it? Yeah, maybe!
衣装もコスチュームもオシャレ！
The outfits and costumes are so stylish!
2人のね、声にめちゃくちゃ合う曲を選んでますので、ちょっと堪能していただけたら。
We chose a song that fits both of their voices amazingly well, so I hope you enjoy it.
そうですね、あのセットリは決めさせていただきました。ありがとー！
That's right, we got to decide the setlist. Thank you!
なのでちょっと堪能していただけると嬉しいなと思います。
We'd be super happy if you can fully enjoy it.
では我々は一緒にちょっと客席に行きましょう。
Now, let's head over to the audience seats together.
オッケーです。
Okay.
ゆっくり休んでください。行ってきまーす。がんばれー！
Take it easy. Have fun! Do your best!
見てるよ。ワーシ、ワーシ、ワーシ、チュウ・ユー・アンド・ミー、ノウ？
Watching you. Watch, watch, watch, choose you and me, you know?
イギリスタイム、イギリスタイム、大丈夫ですか？
English time, English time, are you okay?
大丈夫ですか？
Are you okay?
英語、英語話せるかな？まあ、話せなくてもいいよ。
Can you speak English? Well, it's fine even if you can't.
楽しいもん。
It's fun, after all.
レッツシングアソング！
Let's sing a song!
うん、オッケー。
Yeah, okay.
ロック＆ロール！ロック＆ロール！ロック＆ロール！オッケー、ウィーアーロック＆ローリング！
Rock and roll! Rock and roll! Rock and roll! Okay, we're rock and rolling!
アンドナウ、プリーズリスン、エブリワン、トゥー、カゼトイッショニ！
And now, please listen everyone, to "Kaze to Issho ni"!
歩き続けて どこまでゆくの？
How far will you go as you keep on walking?
風にたずねられて 立ちどまる
The wind asks and I stand still
ひとつめのたいこ トクとなって
With the first drum letting out a thump,
たったひとつの いのち はじまった
one single life has begun
ひとつめのたいこ トクとなって
With the first drum letting out a thump,
たったひとつの いのち はじまった
one single life has begun
歩き続けて どこまで ゆくの？
How far will you go as you keep on walking?
風に たずねられて たちどまる
The wind asks and I stand still
ひとつめの だいこ ドクンと なって
With the first drum letting out a thump,
たった ひとつの いのち はじまった
One single life has begun
やがて なにかを もとめて
Before long, seeking for something
小さな 手のひらを開いて
You spread open your little palms
誕生日 祝う ローソク ふえたけど
The candles for your birthday have increased, but
たった ひとつの ふるさと 旅立った
You start a journey, away from your only home
いまも なにかを もとめて
Even now, you look for something
大きな ひとみが かがやいて
With your big eyes shining
きみの ポケットの なかには
Inside your pocket there are...
いくつもの であい いくつもの わかれ
Countless meetings, countless partings
まぼろしの ような おもいでも すこし
And a few memories which seem like illusions
歩き続けて どこまで ゆくの？
How far will you go as you keep on walking?
風に たずねられた そらをみる
The wind asks and you look to the sky
歩き続けて どこまで ゆこうか
We keep on walking, so where shall we go?
風と いっしょに また 歩き出そう
Together with the wind, let's start walking again
大地 ふみしめ どこまでも ゆこう
Let's step firmly on the earth and go anywhere
めざした あの夢は つかむまで
Until we grasp the dream we were aiming for
大地 ふみしめ どこまでも ゆこう
Let's step firmly on the earth and go anywhere
めざした あの夢は つかむまで
Until we grasp the dream we were aiming for
ララララララ…
La la la la...
もう忘れてしまったかな
I forgot it already
夏の木陰に座ったまま、氷菓を口に放り込んで風を待っていた
I was sitting in the shade of the summer, throwing ice cream into my mouth and waiting for the wind
もう忘れてしまったかな世の中の全部嘘ばかり
I wonder if I’ve forgotten all of the world’s lies
本当の価値を二人で探しに行こうと笑ったこと
I laughed to go find the real value
忘れないように 色褪せないように
Don’t forget, don’t fade
形に残るものが全てじゃないように
So that everything that remains in shape is not everything
言葉をもっと教えて 夏が来るって教えて
Tell me more words, tell me that summer is coming
僕は描いている 目に映ったのは夏の亡霊だ
I’m drawing the summer ghost in my eyes
風にスカートが揺れて
The skirt sways in the wind,
思い出なんて忘れて
forgetting all about memories.
浅い呼吸をする
I take a shallow breath,
汗を拭うって夏めく
wiping sweat as summer approaches.
もう忘れてしまったかな
I wonder if I've forgotten it already,
夏の木陰に座った頃 遠くの丘から顔を出した雲があったじゃないか
when I sat in the summer tree shade, and a cloud peeked out from a distant hill.
君はそれを掴もうとして 馬鹿みたいに空を切った手で
You tried to grab it, cutting through the sky like a fool,
僕は紙に雲一つを描いて 笑って握って見せて
while I drew a single cloud on paper, laughing and holding it out.
忘れないように
So I won't forget,
色褪せないように
so it won't fade away,
歴史に残るものが全てじゃないから
because history's remnants aren't everything.
今だけ顔も失くして 言葉を全部忘れて
Losing even my face right now, forgetting all words,
君は笑ってる 夏を待っている僕ら亡霊だ
you're smiling—we are ghosts waiting for summer.
心をもっと教えて 夏の匂いを教えて
Tell me more of your heart, tell me the scent of summer,
浅い呼吸をする
and I take a shallow breath.
忘れないように
So I won't forget,
色褪せないように
so it won't fade away,
心に響くものが全てじゃないから
because things that echo in the heart aren't everything.
言葉をもっと教えて
Tell me more words,
さよならだって教えて
tell me even 'goodbye'.
今も見るんだよ 夏に咲いている花に亡霊を
Even now I see it—ghosts in the flowers blooming in summer.
言葉じゃなくて時間を
Not words, but time,
時間じゃなくて心を
not time, but the heart.
浅い呼吸をする
I take a shallow breath,
汗を拭うって夏めく
wiping sweat as summer approaches.
夏の匂いがする
There's the scent of summer.
もう忘れてしまったかな
I wonder if I've forgotten it already,
夏の木陰に座ったまま アイスを口にほり込んで風を待っていた
sitting in the summer tree shade, stuffing ice cream in my mouth and waiting for the wind.
というわけで、花に亡霊でした！
And that was 'Hana ni Bourei'!
あずき先輩！ようこそ！
Azuki-senpai! Welcome!
いらっしゃいませー！
Welcome in!
いぇーい！
Yay!
あなたのハートをゼロゲッター！
Zero-getter for your heart!
というわけで、あずきでーす！
And I'm Azuki!
すごい素敵なライブにご招待いただきありがとうございます！
Thank you so much for inviting me to such a wonderful live!
こちらこそご出演いただきありがとうございます！
Thank you so much for performing with us!
この曲はですね、あのあずき先輩に歌いたい曲アンケートみたいなのを...すごい前にね、しましたね
This song... we did a survey a while ago asking what songs you'd want to sing with Azuki-senpai...
そちらで、ころねと一緒に歌いたい曲のところに書いてくださっていた楽曲でして
And you wrote this as a song you'd want to sing together with Korone.
やっぱり、『夏』って聞いて、この曲は外せないなと思いまして
When I heard 'summer', I thought we couldn't leave this song out.
しかもあの、アコースティックにめちゃくちゃ合う！
Plus, it fits acoustic style so well!
コメント欄でもあったんですけど、これ、あずきっちのお箱やん！みたいな
There were comments saying, 'This is Azuki's specialty song!'
でも、ころねちゃんも歌ってるの聴けて、この夏の終わりに歌いたいなと思って選びました
But I wanted to hear Korone sing it too, and sing it at the end of summer, so I chose it.
浄化されました！横で歌ってて、いや本当に良かったし...
I was purified! Singing right next to you, it was truly wonderful...
このアコースティックとかで歌ったことって...
Have you ever sung in this acoustic style...?
あ、でも、あんまりないかも！
Ah, not very often, maybe!
ころねちゃんと一緒に歌うことで、なんかこう...
And singing together with Korone-chan, it felt like...
えっ、『あずころある』、『あずころある』、『あずころあるぞ』というコメントをちらほら見かけまして
I saw comments popping up saying 'AzuKoro is here', 'AzuKoro is real'...
見ました！見ました！嬉しい！
We saw it! We saw it! I'm so happy!
あずき先輩の透き通ってる声を...
Azuki-senpai's crystal clear voice...
みんなね、よかった、みんなって言ってくれてるみたいです。
Everyone says they're glad, it seems.
よかったよかった！ありがとうございます。
I'm so glad! Thank you so much.
では、なんと？
Now then, what is it?
Xトレンド1位！ええー！嬉しい！
X trend #1! Ehh! I'm so happy!
みんなありがとうー！ありがとうございます！
Thank you everyone! Thank you so much!
もっともっと飛び出しちゃってくださーい。
Please keep jumping out even more!
嬉しい！はい、ありがとう！
Happy! Yes, thank you!
それではですね、もっと語りたいこともあるんですけども。
Now then, there's even more we want to talk about, but...
そろそろ次の曲に行きたいと思うのですが。
...we'd like to move on to the next song soon.
え、次のメンバーをまず呼び込みたいと思いますよ。みお先輩とビブー...
Um, first we'd like to invite the next members. Mio-senpai and Biboo...
みおちゃんビブー！
Mio-chan, Biboo!
すすす...やー！
Su-su-su... Ya!
おお！元気元気！りりお待ってる！元気元気！
Oh! Energetic! Ririon is waiting! Energetic!
すごい、なんかちょっとえもくてしっとりみたいな。
Amazing, somehow a bit emotional and mellow.
ね、しっとりにしたね。
Right, we made it mellow.
いや、そうですね。二人でしたからね。あれあれでした。それからだったから？
Well, that's right. Because it was just the two of us. That's how it was.
二人は元気してたんですかね？え、なんかすごい！すごい！
I wonder if those two were doing well? Eh, amazing! Amazing!
はい、えらいね。えらい？えらい！
Yes, good job. Good? Good!
えらい、えらい、えもい！えもい、えもい、えらい！エモーショナル？エモーショナルね！
Good, good, emotional! Emotional, emotional, good! Emotional? Emotional, right!
はい、エモーショナルにお届けしております。
Yes, we are delivering it emotionally.
あ、でですね、ここでちょっと梓先輩とお着替えに。はい、一緒に。お願いいたします。
Now then, Azki-senpai and I are going to change clothes. Yes, together. Please.
でもエモーショナルといえば、ね、ロックンロールかと思っていた、カリス先輩とビブーの風一緒にもめちゃよかったですよ。ありがとうございます。
Speaking of emotional, we thought it would be rock and roll, but Karis-senpai and Biboo's wind together was also really great. Thank you.
元気！はい！ふふふ。
Energetic! Yes! Hehe.
なんだろう、みんなえ、ロックじゃないの？みたいな、戸惑ってるのも。
I wonder, everyone, eh, isn't it rock? Like, being confused too.
あ、動揺した！早い！早い！動揺早い！はい！
Ah, flustered! Fast! Fast! Flustered too fast! Yes!
というわけでき、夏はね、エモい曲が多い感じですが、次からはどうなるのか？
So, summer has a lot of emotional songs, but what will happen from the next one?
ここからは3曲続けてお届けいたします。
From here on, we will deliver 3 songs in a row.
次の曲はですね、こちらの梓先輩、みお先輩、ビブーちゃんの3人に歌っていただきますので。頑張ってー！
The next song will be sung by these three: Azki-senpai, Mio-senpai, and Biboo-chan. Do your best!
それではしばらくバイバイです。みんな頑張ってねー！がんばりよー！
Well then, goodbye for a while. Everyone do your best! Do your best!
ここで一発やっぱロックンロール？ロックンロール？
A single shot of rock and roll here after all? Rock and roll?
動揺してないこと。戸惑ってるの。
Not being flustered. Being confused.
はい、というわけで、まあここから3曲続くんですけど、じゃあこの3人で歌わせていただきます。それでは聞いてください、スパークル。
Yes, so, well, 3 songs will continue from here, but these 3 will sing it. Then please listen, Sparkle.
まだこの世界は 僕を飼いならしたいみたいだ
This world still seems to want to keep on taming me.
望み通りだろう 美しくもがくよ
Just as they wish, right? I'll beautifully struggle against it.
互いの砂時計 眺めながらキスをしようよ
Let me kiss you, watching each other's sand glasses.
「さよなら」から一番 遠い 場所で待ち合わせよう
Let's meet up where the farthest place from goodbye is.
ついに時はきた 昨日までとは序章で
The time has finally come over the prologue until yesterday.
飛ばし読みでいいから ここからが僕だよ
You can skim it as my main chapter starts from here.
経験と知識と カビの生えかかった勇気を持って
Drawing on my past experience, knowledge, and mildewy courage,
いまだかつてないスピードで 君のもとへダイブを
I'll dive to you at a speed higher than ever before.
まどろみの中で 生生しいコーラに ここでじゃないどこかを 夢見たよ
In a drowse over the lukewarm cola, I dreamed of a place different from here.
教室の窓の外に 電車に揺られ 運ばれる朝に
Outside the windows of my classroom, in the morning while I'm jolted in a train.
運命だとか未来とかって 言葉がどれだけ手を伸ばそうとも
Words like fate or future, no matter how far they reach for,
届かない場所で僕ら恋をする
we will fall in love in a place where they can't get at.
時計の針も二人を 横目にしながら進む
The clock hands proceed taking a side glance at us.
こんな世界を二人で 一生 いや、何章でも 生き抜いていこう
In such a world, throughout our lifetime, no, in any number of chapters, let's live on together.
いき抜いて ゆこう
Let's live on...
はじめましてなんてさ
Saying 'Nice to meet you'...
遥かあなたへと遠くへやって
...driving it far off into the distance,
千年周期を
a thousand-year cycle
一日で息しよう
breathed out in a single day.
辞書にある言葉で
In words found in a dictionary,
出来上がった世界を憎んだ
I hated the world built upon them.
万華鏡の中で
Inside a kaleidoscope,
八月のある朝
on a certain morning in August,
君は僕の前で
you stood right before me
はにかんではすましてみせた
and shyly put on a straight face,
この世界の教科書のような笑顔で
with a smile just like a textbook of this world.
烏滸がましい日々を 規格外の意味を 息きたていいから望んだよ
Presumptuous days, off-spec meanings—I wished for them, no matter how breathless.
そうしたらドアの外に 君が全部抱えて立っていたよ
And then, outside the door, you were standing there holding everything.
運命だとか未来とかって 言葉がどれだけ手を伸ばそうとも届かない場所で
In a place where words like 'fate' or 'future' can never reach, no matter how far they stretch their hands,
僕ら遊ぼうか
let's play together.
愛しかったさえも
Even the things I loved so dear
君の匂いがした
carried the scent of you.
歩き出したさえも
Even the steps I took
その笑い声がした
carried the sound of your laughter.
いつか消えてなくなる
Everything of yours that will someday vanish
君の全てを この目に焼き付けておくことは もう権利なんかじゃない 義務だと思うんだ
and burning it all into my eyes—I believe that is no longer just a right, but my duty.
義務だと思うんだ
I believe it is my duty.
運命だとか未来とかって 言葉がどれだけ手を伸ばそうとも届かない場所で
In a place where words like 'fate' or 'future' can never reach, no matter how far they stretch their hands,
僕ら恋いをする
we fall in love.
時計の針も二人を 横目に見ながら進む
The clock hands keep moving, taking a side glance at the two of us.
そんな世界を二人で 一生いや、何章でも 生き抜いていこう
In such a world, throughout our lifetime, no, through any number of chapters, let's live on together.
ああ
Ah...
グラウンド駆け抜くあなたの背中は 空に浮かんだ雲よりも自由で
Running across the ground, your back was freer than the clouds floating in the sky.
ノートに並んだ四角い文字さえも すべてを照らす光に見えた
Even the square letters lined up in a notebook seemed to shine like a light illuminating everything.
好きという気持ちが分からなくて
I didn't understand the feeling of "like"
二度とは戻らないこの時間が
This time that will never return
その意味をあたしに教えてくれた
Taught me its meaning.
あなたと過ごした日々をこの胸に焼き付けよう
Let's burn the days I spent with you into this chest
思い出せなくても大丈夫なように
So that I'll be fine even if I don't remember them
いつか他の誰かを好きになったとしても
Even if I fall in love with someone else someday
あなたはずっと特別で 大切で
You will always be special and precious
またこの季節が めぐってくる
And this season will come around again.
いつまでも忘れないと あなたが言ってくれた夏
The summer you said you would never forget
時間が流れ 今頃あたしは涙がこぼれてきた
Time has passed, and now, tears are spilling out.
皆さん、お待たせしました！
Everyone, thank you for waiting!
ちょっと生ならではという感じで
In a true live, spontaneous fashion,
ゲリラ不具合の機材トラブルが起きてしまいまして
suddenly running into unexpected equipment trouble,
今のところ、あの、ゲームも分かってないんですけど
and right now, well, we don't even know what's going on...
わお！わお！わお！
Woah! Woah! Woah!
あっ、新春にしょー、えー、ブロークン・ザ・ストリート！
Ah, right at the start of the year—uh, Broken The Street!
お待たせしました、復旧したので
Sorry to keep you waiting, we're back up and running,
初めてね、ガーネットからはじめさせていただこうと思って
First, we thought we'd start with Garnet.
ます、みなさんお待たせしてごめんね。
Everyone, sorry to keep you waiting.
ちょっとピリピリってなってみたり耳とかも
With things getting a bit static, and our ears...
えー調子合わせながら、このアコースティックライブで耳治していたいただければと
Adjusting the tuning, we hope you can rest your ears in this acoustic live.
思います。はい、はい。
We think so. Yeah, yeah.
ではウィングさんもありがとうございます。
And Wing-san, thank you too.
添えていただきありがとうございます。
Thank you for accompanying us.
では行きますか。
Shall we get going?
はい。
Yeah.
オッケー？
Okay?
オッケー、オッケー。
Okay, okay.
グランド駆けてく あなたの背中は
Your back running across the grounds
空に浮かんだ 雲よりも自由で
Is freer than the clouds floating in the sky
ノートに並んだ 四角い文字さえ
Even the square letters lined up in my notebook
すべてを照らす 光に見えた
Looked like light that illuminates everything
好きという気持ちが 分からなくて
Not understanding the feeling of "like,"
二度と還らない この時間が
This time that will never return
その意味を あたしに教えてくれた
Taught me its meaning.
あなたと過ごした 日々をこの胸に焼き付けよう
Let's burn the days I spent with you into this heart
思い出せなくても 大丈夫なように
So that I'll be fine even if I don't remember them,
いつか他の誰かを 好きになったとしても
Even if I come to like someone else someday,
あなたははずっと 特別で大切で
You will always be special and precious,
またこの季節がめぐってくる
And this season will come around again.
はじめて二人で話した放課後
The after-school when we talked for the first time,
誰も知らない笑顔探していた
I was looking for a smile that no one knew.
遠くであなたのしゃべってる声になぜか胸が痛くなったの
At your voice frolicking in the distance, my heart started to hurt.
変わっていく事を怖がってたの
I was afraid of things changing,
ずっと友達のままでいれる気がした
I felt like we could stay friends forever.
終わってく物など無いと思った
I thought there was nothing that would end
果てしない時間の中で あなたに出会えた事が
In the endless time, the fact that I could meet you
何よりもあたしを強くしてくれたね
Made me stronger than anything else.
夢中でかける明日にたどり着いたとしても
Even if I reach the tomorrow I'm running toward intensely,
あなたははずっと 特別で大切で
You will always be special and precious,
またこの季節がやってくる
And this season will come around.
いつまでも忘れないとあなたが言ってくれた夏
The summer you said you would never forget,
時間が流れ今頃あたしは涙がこぼれてきた
Time flows, and now tears are spilling out.
あなたと過ごした 日々をこの胸に焼き付けよう
Let's burn the days I spent with you into this heart
思い出せなくても大丈夫なように
So that I'll be fine even if I don't remember them,
いつか他の誰かを好きになったとしても
Even if I come to like someone else someday,
あなたははずっと 特別で大切で
You will always be special and precious,
またこの季節がめぐってくる
And this season will come around again.
終わってくものなどないとあの時は思った
At that time, I thought there was nothing that would end.
果てしない時間の中であなたに出会えたことが
In the endless time, the fact that I could meet you
何よりも私を強くしてくれたね
Made me stronger than anything else.
巡りかける明日にたどり着いたとしても
Even if I reach the tomorrow I'm running toward,
あなたははずっと
You will always...
特別で
Be special...
大切で
And precious...
またこの季節がやってくる
And this season will come around again.
いつまでも忘れないとあなたが言ってくれた夏
The summer you said you would never forget,
時が流れ今頃あたしは涙がこぼれてきた
Time flows, and now tears are spilling out.
あなたと過ごした 日々をこの胸に焼き付けよう
Let's burn the days I spent with you into this heart
思い出せなくても大丈夫なように
So that I'll be fine even if I don't remember them,
いつか他の誰かを好きになったとしても
Even if I come to like someone else someday,
あなたははずっと 特別で大切で
You will always be special and precious,
またこの季節がめぐってくる
And this season will come around again.
はるか遠く 好きになったとしても あなたは
Even if I fell in love with you from afar,
ずっと 特別で 大切で
you'd always be special, so precious to me.
またこの季節が 巡ってく
This season comes around once again.
打上花火
[Title: Uchiage Hanabi]
あの日見渡した渚を 今も思い出すんだ
I can still remember the shore we saw that day,
砂の上に刻んだ言葉 君の後ろ姿
the words we wrote in the sand, the sight of you as you turned away.
寄り添う波が足元を よぎり何かを掬う
The waves ebb and flow across my feet, carrying something away,
夕凪の中日暮れだけが 通り過ぎていく
in the evening calm, only the twilight passes us by.
パッと光って咲いた 花火を見ていた
We watched fireworks blooming in a flash of light.
きっとまだ終わらない夏が
Surely this summer is far from over,
曖昧な心を 溶かして繋いだ
unraveling our uncertain hearts and tying them together,
この夜が続いて欲しかった
I wanted this night to go on forever.
あの日君と同じ 花火を見られるかなって
"I wonder how many more times I'll be able to see the same fireworks as you?"
笑う顔に何が出来るだろうか
What can I do for that smiling face?
傷つくこと喜ぶこと 繰り返す波と情動 焦燥最終列車の音
Being hurt, feeling happy, repetitive waves and emotion, impatience, the sound of the last train.
何度でも言葉にして 君を呼ぶよ
I'll put it into words again and again and call to you.
波間を選びもう一度 もう二度と悲しまずに済むように
I'll choose the space between the waves, one more time, so that you never have to be sad again.
はッと息を呑めば消えちゃいそうな光が きっとまだ胸に住んでいた
If I gasp, the light that looks like it might disappear surely remained within my heart.
手を伸ばせば触れた あったかい未来は ひそかに二人を見ていた
The warm future I touched when I reached out my hand was secretly watching us.
パッと花火が 夜に咲いた
Fireworks suddenly bloomed in the night,
fireworks suddenly bloomed in the night.
夜に咲いて 静かに消えた
Bloomed in the night and disappeared silently.
静かに消えた 離さないで
Disappeared silently... Don't let go,
離れないで もう少しだけ もう少しだけ もう少しだけ このままで
don't go away, just a little longer, just a little longer, just a little longer, let us stay like this.
あの日見渡した渚を 今も思い出すんだ 砂の上に刻んだ言葉 君の後ろ姿
I can still remember the shore we saw that day, the words we wrote in the sand, the sight of you as you turned away.
パッと光って咲いた 花火を見ていた きっとまだ終わらない夏が 曖昧な心を溶かして繋いだ
We watched fireworks blooming in a flash of light. Surely this summer is far from over, unraveling our uncertain hearts and tying them together.
この夜が続いて欲しかった
I wanted this night to go on forever.
聞いて欲しかった…
I wanted you to hear it...
♪
♪ (Humming / Instrumental)
♪ (Piano Instrumental)
はい、ということで、かりりんちゃんと打ち上げ花火を歌させていただきました〜！
So, Kari-rin and I got to sing
"Uchiage Hanabi" together!
花火きれいでした！
The fireworks were so pretty!
やぁ、楽しかった！
Man, that was fun!
どうでしたか？
How was it?
わぁ、とても楽しかったよ。
Wow, it was so much fun.
ええ、かりりんちゃんとこうやってね、デュエットできる日が来るとは。
I never thought the day would come
when I could duet with Kari-rin like this.
もはやもう本当に、地声もして低い声で。
Seriously, I even used my normal voice
for the low parts.
ぼくだってわかった、めちゃめちゃかっこよかった！
I knew it, you were so cool!
ありがとう！もうコントラストがすごい好きだから、そう低い声でやりたいなと思って。
Thank you! I really love the contrast,
so I wanted to sing the low parts.
そうね、男性パートをね歌って、歌ってくださいました。かりりんちゃんありがとう。
Yeah, you sang the male part.
Thank you so much, Kari-rin.
こちらこそありがとうございます。楽しかった！
Thank you so much too. It was fun!
楽しかった！ということで、ここでねまた
It was fun! And with that, here again...
メンバーのみんなを、え、呼びたいと思います。全員しゅごー！
I'd like to call everyone else out.
Everyone, assemble!
カモン！イエーイ！カモンカモンカモンカモン！
Come on! Yay!
Come on, come on, come on, come on!
イエーイ！イエーイ！イエーイ！イエーイ！はい、最高だった！
Yay! Yay! Yay! Yay!
Yes, that was the best!
もっとずっと最高です。凄きでした、本当に。凄きでした。ありがとうございます。
It's always the best.
It was truly amazing. Thank you!
ということでですね、改めてまして、本日はアコースティックライブ、え、出演いただき、そして見ていただき、ありがとうございます！
Thank you so much for performing
and watching today's acoustic live!
ありがとうございました！ありがとう！サンキュー！サンキューガイズ！
Thank you very much!
Thank you! Thank you guys!
もう本当に、選曲神だったなって自分で思うぐらいね、皆さんのお声がジガジサンするぐらい皆さんが本当に素晴らしくて幸せなひとときを過ごさせていただきました。ありがとうございます！
I honestly feel like this setlist was god-tier...
We got to spend such a happy moment together.
ありがとうございました！魅力ねタイムよ。はい！
Thank you very much!
Charm-point time. Yes!
というわけですね、なんと次が最後の曲になってしまいました！
So with that said, incredibly,
the next song is already our final one!
えー！いま来たばかりなのに！ひと晩かりだよ！ラストはね、この全員揃って歌いますので、
Eh?! We just got here!
And for the last one, we're all singing together...
お楽しみにしていただけると嬉しいんですが、ラストに行く前に、ちょっとせっかくなんで、ピアノの前でスクショタイムとか。
Before we go to the last song,
how about a screenshot time in front of the piano?
お！お、しましょう！思い出を、思い出を、思い出を！皆さんもとってください。あ、じゃこや、じゃこや声をしゃがんで。
Oh, let's do it! Memories!
Everyone take one too. Squat down.
いーえい！おお、うれしい！さいちゃんかっこいいよ！うわい！
Yay! Oh, how nice!
Sai-chan looks cool! Wow!
イエーイ！イエーイ！イエーイ！ああ、いい写真！イエーイ！イエーイ！
Yay! Yay! Yay!
Ah, great photo! Yay! Yay!
あ、なになになに。あ、みなさんとりました！イエーイ！イエーイ！イエーイ！
Ah, what's going on?
Ah, everyone took it! Yay! Yay! Yay!
はーい、じゃあもどりますか。ぜひぜひツイートしてくださいね。ツイートを、ツイートをなになに。アップして。
Alright, shall we go back?
Please make sure to tweet! Upload it.
息すぎた。息すぎた。はしたない。ハシタグよろしく！ありがとうございます！
Out of breath. Unladylike.
Use the hashtag properly! Thank you!
では、ちょっとね、あの最後の曲に行く前に、一言ずついただこうかなと思いますので、ぴーぷーどうだった？
Now, before going to the final song,
I'd like to get a word from everyone. Pipi, how was it?
えーと、めちゃっ楽しかった！みんな、すごいですよね。
Um, it was super fun!
Everyone is amazing, aren't they?
すごくない？
Isn't it amazing?
あ、ありがと。ジャパニーズイズベリーグッド、すごいってコメントいっぱいありました。
Ah, thank you. There were so many comments
saying "Japanese is very good, amazing!"
あれあれあれ。ジャパニーズ、にほんご、もうちょっとむずかしいです。
Oh dear. Japanese... my Japanese
is a bit difficult.
すごかったよ！めちゃプラクティス、してたんだもんね。
It was amazing! You practiced so much,
after all.
そう。あの、ENのね、2月にありました、そちらのアーカイブが9月25とかだったかな。
Yeah. The EN live back in February—
its archive is around September 25th, I think.
もうちょっと見れますので、ぜひ、あのそちらも見てください。ありがとうございます！
You can still watch it a bit more,
so please check that out too. Thank you!
そして、カリ先輩。あたし、もっと歌いたかった。この夜が続いて欲しかった。
And, Calli-senpai. I wanted to sing more.
I wanted this night to keep going.
だから、そのあと3曲ぐらいは歌いたかった。
So I wanted to sing about
3 more songs after that.
あはは、本当に楽しかった。あの、実は私むかし、あの、ま、スタートから、あの、ま、あの、3Dがゲットした時、あの、ずっと毎回、あの生ライブやってた。
Ahaha, it was really fun. Actually, I...
from the start, when I got my 3D model...
ああ、そうだも3Dライブ、そうそうそう、やってたからさ
Ah, right, the 3D live, yeah, yeah, since we were doing that...
まあ超久しぶりですね、ずっとまたやりたかったけど、ま、機会ががなくて
It's been a super long time. I wanted to do it again, but there wasn't really a chance.
結構収録がね、あの、入るようになったりとかもしましたからね。
Recording sessions started happening more often, too.
そうだね、だから本当にありがとうございます。とっても楽しかったです。
That's right. So thank you so much, it was so much fun.
なんかテレテレしてる。
You look all flustered.
めちゃくちゃかっこよかった！
It was super cool!
あの、カリ先輩は今日ね、水着の5周年のライブから
Calli-senpai, today, right after the 5th anniversary live stream...
駆け付けで
rushed right over here.
5周年水着ライブ、間に合うわけないじゃんそんなこと。
5th anniversary live? There's no way you could make it in time.
でも、あれもチェックしてほしい。
But please check that out too!
ね、そう、ぜひですね、こちらアーカイブもあるので
Yeah, definitely, there's an archive for that too, so
忙しすぎると楽しいからさ、キューシ
It's so busy it's fun!
こちらこそありがとうございます。
Thank you very much to you too.
そして、ミオ先輩！
And Mio-senpai!
はい！いや、こうやってね、みんなとね、一緒に歌うっていうことが楽しかったね。すごいね。
Yes! Man, singing together with everyone like this was so fun. It's amazing.
あの、今日貴重な時間を貰えて本当に嬉しかったです。本当にありがとうございます。
I was really happy to receive this precious time today. Thank you so much.
いや、こちらこそありがとうございます！
No, thank you very much!
いや、ホロタ、ミオ先輩はソロライブ終わったばっかりで、そっちも大変だったのに
Mio-senpai just finished her solo live, even though that must have been so tough,
関わらずね、出演してくださって。
she still came and performed.
でも、なんか出たいなって思ったんだけど、なんかどうなってんか不安だから、ちょっと曲数は少なくしてもらって
But I thought I wanted to appear, and since I was worried about how it would turn out, I had them reduce the number of songs a bit,
で、曲数が少ない
but the number of songs is a bit small!
そうなんですよ、気遣いいただきありがとうございます。でも出てよかった。
That's right, thank you for your consideration. But I'm glad I appeared.
そうそう、ソロライブも本当最高だったし、アーカイブありますんで
That's right, your solo live was truly amazing, and there's an archive,
ぜひ皆さん見てください。チェックしてね！
so everyone please go watch it. Check it out!
そして、あずき先輩！
And Azki-senpai!
はい！いや本当に今日、いい時間を、最高の時間を過ごさせていただきました。
Yes! Man, today I really got to spend such a wonderful, the best time.
見てくださった方もありがとうございましたっていうのと
Thank you to everyone who watched,
今回ね、こえちゃんが主催してくれて、このライブがありますので、こえちゃんありがとうと
and since Koe-chan organized this live this time, thank you Koe-chan,
こちらこそありがとうございます！
thank you so much!
ビーグさんもあの素敵な演奏もありがとうございました。
And Vig-san, thank you for the wonderful performance as well.
本当に最高です、素晴らしい。
It's truly the best, wonderful.
いや、またインサマーですか？インウィンターあるんですか？
Man, is there an In Summer? Is there an In Winter?
え、やりたいなっていう気持ちを込めて、そう、その気持ちを込めてね、
Huh? Wanting to do it, putting that feeling into it, yeah, putting that feeling in,
4回できますよね、こうなればね、曲次第ですもんね。
we can do it four times, right? If it's like this, it depends on the songs.
今日のライブの感想とかもね、ぜひぜひ教えて
Please definitely let us know your thoughts on today's live,
いただけたらなと思います。ありがとうございました！
if you could. Thank you very much!
お願いしまーす。そしてあずき先輩は
Please do. And Azki-senpai has
11月にソロライブが、ありがとうございます！
her solo live in November, thank you!
はい、ありますので、よかったらぜひ見に来ていただけたら嬉しいです。めちゃくちゃ楽しみににしております。
Yes, so, if you'd like, we'd be happy if you came to see it. We're looking forward to it so much.
放送直前です、今。
It's right before the broadcast right now.
本当にね、はい、配信チケットもありますんでね、ぜひ皆さんご覧ください。よろしくお願いします。
Truly, yeah, there are streaming tickets too, so please everyone check it out. Thank you.
はい、というわけでですね、ま、今日あの本当にこの主催を
Yes, so, today, organizing this,
してみたのは、みんなの歌聴いて、みんなと一緒に歌ってみたいな気持ちもすごくありまして、そしてピアノと一緒に歌いたいていう気持ちもありまして、
doing it was because I wanted to listen to everyone sing, sing together with everyone, and also sing along with the piano,
やったんですけど、本当に最高の時間でした。ありがとうございました！
so we did it, and it was truly the best time. Thank you very much!
ありがとうございます！
Thank you!
ありがとうございます！ありがとうございます！
Thank you! Thank you!
最後の曲はちょっとね、名残惜しいんですけど
The last song is a bit bittersweet,
はい、あの、このまま歌っていただきたいと思いますけど、皆さん何曲目だと思いますか？
yes, we'd like you to keep listening, but what song do you think it is?
What song do you think we're going to sing last, chat? Let's see your guesses.
ラストソング、ラストソング What do you think?
Last song, last song. What do you think?
Last song? Guess? Guess?
ラストソングをゲスできるのか？ゲスできる？うーん、できるかな？
Can you guess the last song? Can you guess? Hmm, can you?
え？
Huh?
SS！SS！あ、SS！
SS! SS! Ah, SS!
確かに、アセーシュアアーカイブ、あ、最初に流れてたか。
True, ASW... archive, oh, it was playing at the start.
歌うって思うよねって話してましたね。
We were talking about how you'd think we'd sing it.
だから正解もありそうですよ。正解も、ありそう！ありそう！ありそう！
So there might be a correct answer. A correct answer? Seems likely! Seems likely!
すごい。でも結構割れてますが
Amazing. But opinions are pretty divided,
結構夏の歌といえば、というこの曲で締めさせていただきたいと思います。
but we'd like to close with this song, which is quintessential to summer.
はい。
Yes.
それでは聴いてください。「secret base ～君がくれたもの～」。
Then please listen to "secret base ~Kimi ga Kureta Mono~".
君と夏の終わり 将来の夢
I'll never forget being with you at the end of summer,
大きな希望 忘れない
with our dreams of the future and big hopes.
10年後の8月 また出会えるのを 信じて
I believe that ten years later in August, we'll meet again.
最高の思い出を…
Such great memories...
出逢いは ふとした 瞬間
We met in a sudden instant
帰り道の 交差点で
at the intersection on the way home
声をかけてくれたね
And you called out to me,
一緒に帰ろう
Let's go home together
カバンで顔を隠しながら
Hiding my face behind my bag,
本当はとってもとっても嬉しかったよ
The truth is, I was so, so happy.
ああ 花火が夜空 きれいに咲いて ちょっとセツナク
Ah, fireworks bloom so cleanly in the night sky, a bit bittersweet.
ああ 風が時間とともに 流れる
Ah, the wind flows along with time.
嬉しくって 楽しくって 冒険もいろいろしたね
It was so happy, so fun, we went on various adventures.
二人の 秘密の 基地の中
Inside our secret base for two.
君が最後まで 心から 「ありがとう」叫んでいたこと 知っていたよ
I knew that right until the end, you shouted "Thank you" from the bottom of your heart.
涙をこらえて 笑顔でさようなら せつないね 最高の思い出を
Holding back tears, saying goodbye with a smile—how heartbreaking, our best memory.
君が最後まで 心から 「ありがとう」叫んでいたこと 知っていたよ
I knew that right until the end, you shouted "Thank you" from the bottom of your heart.
涙をこらえて 笑顔でさようなら せつないね
Holding back tears, saying goodbye with a smile—so heartbreaking,
最高の 思い出を
Our best memory...
ああ 夏休みも あと少しで 終わっちゃうから
Ah, summer vacation will be ending soon,
ああ 太陽と月 仲良くして
Ah, the sun and moon get along so well.
悲しくって 寂しくって 喧嘩もいろいろしたね
Sad and lonely, we had all kinds of fights too.
二人の 秘密の 基地の中
Inside our secret base for two.
君が最後まで 心から 「ありがとう」叫んでいたこと 知っていたよ
I knew that right until the end, you shouted "Thank you" from the bottom of your heart.
涙をこらえて 笑顔でさようなら せつないよね
Holding back tears, saying goodbye with a smile—how heartbreaking,
最高の 思い出を
Our best memory...
突然の 転校で
Because of a sudden transfer,
どうしようもなく 手紙 書くよ 電話もするよ
With no other choice, I'll write letters and call you.
忘れないでね 僕のことを いつまでも 二人の 秘密の 基地の中
Don't forget about me, forever inside our secret base for two.
描く未来図は 模するよ 忘れないでね 僕のことを
I'll trace our future dreams. Don't forget about me,
いつまでも ふたりの 秘密の 基地の中
Forever inside our secret base for two.
君と夏の終わり ずっと話して 夕日を見てから 星を眺め
Talking through the end of summer, watching the sunset, gazing at the stars,
君の頬流れた 涙は ずっと忘れない
I will never forget the tears that streamed down your cheeks.
君が最後まで 大きく手を振ってくれたこと きっと忘れない
I will surely never forget how you waved goodbye with big hands until the end.
だからこうして 夢の中で ずっと永遠に
That's why like this, inside my dreams, forever and ever...
君と夏の終わり 将来の夢 大きな希望 忘れられない
The end of summer with you, future dreams, big hopes, unforgettable.
10年後の8月 また出会えるのを 信じて
Believing we can meet again in August, ten years from now.
君が最後まで 心から 「ありがとう」叫んでいたこと 知っていたよ
I knew that right until the end, you shouted "Thank you" from the bottom of your heart.
涙をこらえて 笑顔でさようなら せつないよね
Holding back tears, saying goodbye with a smile—how heartbreaking,
最高の 思い出を
Our best memory...
ありがとう
Thank you!
だって僕は星だから
Just like the shooting star I have become
Stellar Stellar
きっと君もう気付いていた
I'm sure that you've already noticed
僕の心の奥で描いた
The script hidden deep down in my heart
それがこれから話す
that I will now read out, acting the part
陳腐なモノローグさ
A clichéd monologue
ずっと言えない言葉があった
There are so many things I couldn't say out loud
壊せない壁があったんだ
So many walls I could never climb beyond
ずっとさ
It never ends...
ふっと香り立つ朝の匂いが
Sensing the scent of morning wafting in the air
どうしようもなく憎らしくて
I tried to fight it filling me with hate
部屋の隅で膝を抱えて震えていた
I sat in a corner and cried into my knees
太陽なんかいらないから
I don't need the sunshine
明けんでいてで
Can dawn please stay away?
その手を伸ばして
Hold your hand out all the way
誰かに届くように
And reach out to make someone feel
僕だって君と同じ
We're very alike, indeed, both you and me
特別なんかじゃないから
Neither of us is special
そうさ僕は夜を歌うよ Stellar Stellar
So I sing now through this night, Stellar Stellar